and how many times they read it um helps
to answer his question
it helps that self-control
so it's
you know if
if you eat when you're hungry
for the purpose of hunger
then it will be easier for you to catch
your mind when you want to eat for the
purpose of pleasure or distraction or
because you're bored because you saw
some nice food that you wanted always to
eat but you're not really hungry
so all of those things means you're
giving in to the pointless desires that
are not really necessary which means
that's how your mind will control you
then so so
people don't
don't think about it when things are
pleasant because then what you give in you get
because then what you give in you get
rewarded with pleasure but because uh
giving in to such pointless desires
as i said keeps your mind
not tame let's say like that so then
when you experience discomfort when that
same untamed mind starts to resist and
rebel and shout you also can't calm me
down because you've been just like
feeding a dog treats all the time and
not teaching in any discipline then when
that dog gets upset he won't listen to
you when you tell him to shut up or sit
quietly because you haven't trained it
when you could
so that's important to recognize that
it's not just about sort of um
overcoming pain and suffering
pain and suffering
it is but through also
self-control and sense restraint in
regard to pleasures that usually
intoxicate the mind
and that's that self-control that comes
through precepts and sense restraint
after you gain this self-control
then do you still seek pleasures or
do you still seek pleasures or
if you not don't seek it can you have it
without being
attached to it
uh depends
it depends what pleasures
pleasures of food or i don't know
pleasant sights yeah that's fine you you
can have it without being attached but
like sexual pleasures pleasures of the
more intoxicating natures you can't have
those without being attached to them so
it's either or you either give them up
or you're still attached to them you
can't have them and be free from them at
the same time if you understand the
nature of suffering and
how to
achieve freedom from suffering
when you are talking to
some friend or a relative
but you
you can see that the person doesn't
have this
awareness of suffering
how can you help other people
in achieving the awareness
well you can help someone only if they
want to be helped
so you can't make them aware if they
don't want to hear it
but uh if they want to hear it then you
don't really need my advice on how to
help them just tell them exactly what
you just said
so i think the problem is that they
don't want to be helped but you want to
help them still
so try perhaps you know hinting that
they should reconsider whether they need
help or not
but uh sometimes if you come like
head on trying to give them what helped
you will help you as well people will
reject it and they will not respect it
as much because they feel like you're
putting it on to them
but sometimes they they know they want
to
to change and they want to
find the nature of suffering
and but they're
seeking in wrong places they're doing it
outside themselves they don't look
inside do they know they're supposed to look
do they know they're supposed to look
inside
yeah so yeah you can only give them right
so yeah you can only give them right
information but
if they don't follow it means they just
say they want to understand but they're
obviously not doing everything about it
you know everybody wants to be free from
suffering but it doesn't mean that
everybody will make the effort to train
themselves to be free from suffering um
um
how do you train yourself
as i just described um taking on the
precepts the rules of behavior so don't do
the rules of behavior so don't do
unwholesome things by body
speech mind
sense restraint
don't just go to pleasures
blindly then
then
moderate in eating exactly finding the
right reasons for consuming food
mindfulness watchfulness of your
intentions everything the students talk about
and also probably just you know this
recognition of
their situations where
the other side
other either cannot at this particular
point accept any type of help or they're
not really willing so they might be
asking questions like what do i do but
whenever you provide some sort of
suggestion they are just kind of
well that's that's when you're gonna see
whether they want help or not when
people ask you tell them what to do
and they don't do it
it's fine it's not it's not your issue
but uh then you realize okay so they're
not really asking they're asking just in
order to hear what they want to hear but
if you tell them what they don't want to
hear they're not going to do it
which is fine everybody has their
choices but if they come and ask what do
i do what do the buddha teach what is
the practice you tell them okay tell
them clearly this is what it is take it
or leave it basically that's all that's
all the buddha could have done
he often said you know i would present
it and sometimes a person will follow it
and yeah that's pleasing because i
didn't waste my time sometimes i would
present the teaching person we're going
to do the opposite thing well that's
displeasing because i've wasted my time
but either way my mind is not supported
by it
because it's not it's not his
responsibility really
maybe just a very short follow-up
question on this
sometimes when i find myself in this
particular situation i wonder whether
it's um
you know whether
it is
the issue that the other person doesn't
really want to hear or whether
i have not been able to find a way to
communicate something that would
uh sound meaningful to the other person
and what i mean by that is all this all
these different ways that the buddha
uses to convey his message sure there's
a skill in teaching in recognizing
what's valuable but
that is secondary really it's not um
like sometimes people get burdened by
this pressure to help and convey you
know this you must help you but that is
secondary really
what you must do is not lose perspective
and act out of that pressure
then you will be the
most accurate in whatever you say but if
you start really acting out of that
compulsion to help them you are losing
your perspective even if you're just
parroting the teaching it's still you're
doing it now out of that emotional need
to satisfy your own desire of being
heard and whatever else
so you just have to recognize because
sometimes it's better to not say
everything than to give too much information as
than to give too much information as
well but you won't see that if you're if
you're gripped by that no i must help i
must help
yeah and i also have a question in this
connection so i i already asked you in
privately about this so
but maybe some
more information could be helpful um so
the the buddha himself so he sometimes
was asked by just people people i say
like this like just those who want to
live happily at home with their wives
and and sons and and basically he was
telling them you need to
keep five precepts and uh yeah um i
wonder well they obviously believed in
in in
in afterlife
and yeah for them it was meaningful but
do you think that like for people
nowadays who also just want to have this
say worldly happiness uh well it makes
any sense to speak about like five
precepts and maybe they censor strain
yeah yeah of course yeah
as i said in that
not a few rooms ago we did
uh again
the mind is happy or unhappy not because
of the world not because of what's
happening in the world but because
whether the mind is trained or pained or
how much it's trained or tamed
so in other words you can have
everything bad happen around you but if
your mind is trained and calm you will
not be unhappy on account of it
so i think deep down even the most
unrestrained person values
the idea at least of a peaceful mind of
mind that's not disturbed by things he
just doesn't know how to go about it
well five precepts is how you go about
it
so even if you don't believe in what the
buddha said or any other religion and
you're just a pure scientist and you
don't care about the future lives you do
know the value of peace here and now and
it's not going to come to a wild
behavior that's obvious to a 10 year old
boy who knows he doesn't want to do
anything about it but he knows
that he needs to calm down when the
parents tell him to
so um so yeah
you just mentioned the five pieces for
those who don't know
uh the five principles of killing not
stealing not lying
not cheating or engaging in like
extreme levels of sensuality and not
drinking or taking drugs and intoxicants
they will pollute your mindfulness and
awareness of day-to-day life
and then within that you can practice
then the refined precepts of speech
so don't talk unless you have something
to say
uh don't uh don't insult people gossip
spread rumors chit chat just again like
so first it's the physical behavior then
you hone in the world behavior and it's
it's just the training they would have
compared training a wild elephant you
get getting from the wilderness tying
down until he comes down when he comes
down offer him food if he doesn't take
the food and keep him tight and offering
then he takes the food out then he's
ready to listen and and that's how you
develop the training
so it's the same principle really
um yeah but in in this connection like
so people would generally as they agree
that to say normal situation it's good
to follow these rules it makes sense but
let's say yeah like like for the war i
would ask you like the situation that we
are now in so people will say yeah i
mean it's not good to kill in principle
but yeah but i cannot like say lose
everything so well you have a choice either you
so well you have a choice either you
defend and kill or bring break the
precepts or you don't yeah but see if
you if you choose to defend and kill
then you can expect the other party will
do the same so the war will never end
so violence will always bring more
violence so yes somebody has to take it
first and not not do it back
and even then it's honestly that other
people will stop but you don't care
about other people's actions you care
about your mental state and whether you
have found the peace internally
found the peace internally
so that's why dhamma really it's not
compatible if you want to
if you want to
you know govern the world and engage
with the world even the buddha himself
had to make a choice whether he'll be
the supreme
righteous ruler of the world or go and
become the buddha he couldn't do both
he was either or
so this is the same you you have a
choice which one do you value more
um and then take it
take responsibility for it but then you
can't expect results from both
like oh i'm on the peaceful mind
although i am breaking the presets in
quite a serious way
if it comes to killing and so on so but
so but
does it mean that let's say for the
people who
um well have so much attachment to let's
say you know to to to their country or
maybe to kind of their families whatever
may happen
do you think that well
that they are going to be more peaceful
if they uh say
try to endure this even though they
don't understand really the meaning of
this endurance just for for the sake of
keeping precepts or or if they let's say
break them and sort of yeah do
this stuff
well sure i mean the wild elephant
unless until it's trained it will be
more peaceful in the wilderness of
sensuality but that's not going to result in in
but that's not going to result in in
peace and happiness we're talking about
it's just perpetuation of the problem
so then
by perpetuating your attachments you're
perpetuating your basis for suffering
you don't suffer because the war started
you suffer because things that are dear
to you are under a threat
if you have nothing dear to you you
cannot suffer even if you yourself is
being attacked
plain and simple
so if you choose to protect your
attachments that is fine that is your choice but
that is fine that is your choice but
that means okay you are choosing
basically perpetuation of dependence on
things that keep you
uh not calm and not peaceful and at
threat and not at ease
that's that's exactly what it would have
meant by um
acquisitions that was the word
the things that belong to you that they
expose you because of them you suffer
because of them you're liable to
suffering so
and same with the idea of nationality as
well and the country that's like one of the
and the country that's like one of the
subtle thoughts that thoughts that the
monk would abandon first the course
centrality the cause cruelty but then
thoughts of belonging to my clan clan
hood family country all of those ideas
of identity those are also your
possessions and because of that you will suffer
and because of that you will suffer
would buddha
defend his life
while being physically
no
no he said if you have even an evil
thought towards your attackers while
they're butchering you you haven't
fulfilled his instruction
so let alone if you actually fight back
and how would you address the the the
evil thoughts
first by not acting out of them because
the evil thoughts become a problem when
you start doing things on account of
them having the marais in your mind it's not
having the marais in your mind it's not
a problem in itself
but if you do something out of body
because of evil thoughts if you start
saying things because of evil thoughts
that's what the problem is
so don't do anything about body by
speech and then evil thoughts will not
have as much power over you as they did
when you used to act out of them
so like that that wild elephant that's
changed in the beginning every thought
will be thought of that you know great
unrestrained wilderness but once he
comes down gets used to the environment
those thoughts will not be as pressuring
as before
and that's their training being able to
take them without acting out of them
do you believe that we live through our
mind sorry
sorry
i mean to me it seems like we are like
rationalizing everything
and um
that we are not like
leaving from the
from the heart that we are
well again that in itself is a
rationalization that you must live from
the heart who says who said that
we didn't all agree on that not all
people agree with that we all must live
from the heart and what does that mean
for you what does that mean for me what
does that mean give me different things
so then you realize yeah rationalization
some people do it more some people do it
less but
even then
you have to be doing something even if
you think i'll just stop thinking and
live the life fully that's another
rationalization that you're choosing to
act upon
so you want to really recognize like
where are your actions taking you are
they are they adding fuel to the wild
mind or are they calming it
are they helping you
keep an eye on that mind when it changes
or not or are they making you forget
about it
so so that's where the that's where the
practice is
so one comment with regards to this is
um
and i would be happy if you could then maybe
i would be happy if you could then maybe
expand on this or maybe add a few
reflections my my uh experience
my my uh experience
so far was
drawing both of my own personal
experience and also um on the
experiences i've had uh with other
friends and colleagues who are you know
interested in meditation and have
decided to maybe pursue the meditative
path of one way or another
there's just this
other rootlessness in the sense of
rootlessness in the sense of
there's no room for stila whatsoever and
this was you know my experience as well
and listening to this
i was again reminded of this you know
finding myself in certain places uh
um with certain experiences i couldn't
really handle
and i didn't know what to do with them
and i had absolutely no anchoring
whatsoever and what i found helpful some sometimes
and what i found helpful some sometimes
was just you know engaging in something
very physical or something very simple
just so that i was you know anchored and
after that i could pursue
so continue with with say contemplative
practice and whatnot
not putting it aside completely that is
to say but it was through these
experiences that i realized how
important this
anchorage is so that this was my entry
into the realm of sila how
naive i was in a certain sense thinking
that well you know this is yeah okay we
start with silas give me the meat yeah
yeah give me the meat you know what's
really interesting the name but the
veggies just you know i want the raw
stuff
i noticed that this is like a really big
problem in in western practitioners just
willing wanting to just skip this through and i
wanting to just skip this through and i
was just wondering in what way
would it be perhaps possible to
articulate the importance of sea love so
that you know someone in contemporary setting
you know someone in contemporary setting
would realize this without necessarily
having to go
several years and then well in the way
i'm doing it
300 talks on youtube
i don't know how many audio hours just
repeating the same
and it's most of it's exactly for that
reason yeah
because people are like people hear the
buddhist teaching they're interested in
it but then they want to skip the
training part
and then to make things worse you have
modern techniques and centers and
meditations and monasteries that
encourage you to kind of okay yeah keep
it but this is really the meat of the
practice so it becomes even more distant
and people don't even recognize you know
people might take on the sealer but not
recognize how
how the training comes through it
they take the precepts because they're
buddhists and so on but they don't train
in them and there's a big difference
that's why it's it's still about the
paramount in within the first three factors that
in within the first three factors that
they're abandoned
so it's not a small thing basically one
way or the other
um
people's minds generally regardless of
the culture and education everything
else i used to you know acting out of
sensuality acting out of your own
desires which naturally then brings that
whole expectation okay i want to
practice give me the result
and then you know you don't want to be
patient about it and so on so uh
so yeah you just keep repeating it and
those who are willing to hear it will do
so yeah
but my experience so far was that
usually and also don't don't don't give
any compromise there is no oh this is
helpful no it's not the word was quite
clear there is there's no right view
there is no meditation if somebody wants
to practice meditation without the right
view without a virtue
without training in precepts that's not
possible at least not in the buddhist
teaching so
now they can at least know that okay
this teaching this is what's thought i
cannot mistake it for something else or
misrepresent it and then they can choose
to follow a different teacher or
whatever else there's no problem
but the problem is when people
misrepresent what the buddha was
teaching and then think that this is the
practice of dharma it has nothing to do
with it or quite opposite directly
opposite to it and that's why the buddha
would refer to those things like
pernicious views
not because you know people are evil in
them but because see now they think
they're practicing dharma by doing
meditation technique having precepts
secondary over the weekend or something
and now they will not make the effort to
practice the time or find out what a
dharma is because they think that's
that's what a buddha was teaching full
stop and that's the worst
and that's the worst
at least you know if you prefer it and
you do it but at least if you know that
that's not what it was teaching well
there is still a
possibility for you
at some point in the future to come back
to it and maybe do it rightly
but not if you have uh misrepresented it
yeah but i mean but it it seems to me
that well
in the perception of people it seems to
be like logical i mean
this is
it is good to to keep consider some
moral standards
in the normal times but but if you are
threatened so to say they would say yeah
yeah so then you have a choice put your
attachments first or your moral
standards first
but you can't have it both that's why
did you why wouldn't you kill to protect
your family i don't know up to you
i'm not saying you shouldn't you
shouldn't i'm saying what the moral
standards are
so you can't have moral standards intact
and break them it's simply a
contradiction in terms
so if you choose to kill means you chose
to put your attachment first and your
moral standard second if you choose to
not kill means you stayed with your
moral standards choice is yours
either that uh either that moro or that
wife sorry either that moral or a dead wife
sorry either that moral or a dead wife
yeah exactly exactly
this if you have um
my wife this is hypothetically but you
can save
one billion lives
or kill one who wants to kill them yeah
the standards hit the question yeah
so what is the moral question here well
the moral question is that you're
responsible for your choice
so the moral question is that your
choice is not on the level of world and
other people it's on the level of you
choosing to do so yes so if you choose
to kill one person you did commit murder
it doesn't matter if you save thousands
so which is more important to you to
measure by the standards of the world or
to keep your moral standards or at least
the buddhist moral standards do you
think he would
not save one billion life
save one billion life
absolutely not no if if it means killing
yeah absolutely not he's incapable of
killing absolutely impossible
absolutely impossible
and now you create yourself a problem of
another philosophical question not that
i want to get into it but
what who determines the value of life is it
who determines the value of life is it
the sheer quantity of life is better
thousand is better than one
or is there a quality to life
one wise person is better than 100
immortal killers
who decides that
so you're going to end up in a in a big
sort of entanglement
in reality that's going to result in
exactly people doing what they want and
justifying if it's some moral standards
that they themselves are breaking
because they ignore the basic rule is
that doesn't matter what the world says
doesn't matter what a state of the world
is you are responsible for your choices
and your actions
so if you start putting that first
then killing will be felt differently
killing will be felt differently
even if it's i go to harder questions
is a cypher of psychopath who wants to
destroy all earth
and the buddha has power to kill him
yeah so the whole cosmos
okay what would he do not kill him but
he okay
okay that's an easy question that's easy
that's an easy question that's easy
not kill him absolutely
this story there was like one murderous
game and i deserved the one billion
death it was uh my
mother's guy uh anguli malek who was
killing thousands of them
and have a chance but he didn't he was
have a chance but he didn't he was
teaching him dharma
so he got well it's not that's not his
problem thousand people died it's not because
thousand people died it's not because
the buddha didn't kill that guy it's
because that guy chose to kill thousand
people but um i think that he has some
but um i think that he has some
knowledge about this universe also the
perhaps he believed or knew that there
is
the whole stuff will be
rebuilt again maybe but say
following your argument uh he had
knowledge about
the universe greater than ours and he
said you should never kill
so there you go
he probably had even greater reasons
that we can fed him to say no never you
should never kill
yeah no i agree with that
this does this apply
does this apply
where is the border the meaning of life
only to
people or
to
animals and plants and so on where is
the border oh it applies to to any
creatures that are capable of choices
and action which is why animals are so
screwed they can't stop it they don't have
they can't stop it they don't have
enough power
to reflect and
make right choices which is why it's so
hard to leave the animal realm as the
buddha was saying
would have some powers to calm people
down with his essence just to be in
front of them
so
they won't do something they want to do
just through them their emotions
through them their emotions
uh
he no he i mean
yes and no i suppose he couldn't take
control or responsibility for their
actions but
sometimes if people were calmed down by
his demeanor it's because they already
kind of recognized the value of such
demeanor but some people didn't even
recognize that he would have been the
buddha or anything like that
so yes some people were calmed by him
but because they already kind of
valued that type of appearance or
behavior and maybe reminding them of
that okay maybe
okay maybe
a question of
that is related to some of the topics
that we were talking about uh
that's basically in a certain sense some
minor elephant in the room namely the
situation in ukraine
so i was just curious
if you could maybe
share a few words on
how maybe
you as a monastic relate to events of
this sort and what would you suggest or
advice to someone who is still part of
the world so in a certain senses
in one way or another embedded how to
conduct him or herself wisely with regards to
him or herself wisely with regards to
these things so you know uh something
like that happens and then it's all over
the news and you don't want to be
completely flooded by it but in a
certain sense you still because you're
part of the world you still maybe want
to contribute in one way or another or i
don't know
by i don't know helping people who come
over um i can for instance do this in in
the academic setting because there will
be specific things that we can do so you
help those that need help keep the
precepts don't break the precepts they're quite
don't break the precepts they're quite
clear why you should do it you shouldn't
[Music] and
and
yeah probably don't become addicted to
reading news as well
that's quite a thing in itself
so um
yeah again a very simple answer would
you advise it doesn't really matter if
it's a war in ukraine or anywhere else
the the principles remain intact and
changed if and if you want to practice
or at least maintain the framework of
some sort of buddhist practice you have
to put those standards first
how do you define pleasure and
kind can someone get
meditation for pleasure
yeah and be addicted to meditation yeah
that's what we will call wrong addiction
to mindfulness
uh
i don't think you can be addicted to
mindfulness because it's not something you're doing
because it's not something you're doing
but yeah certainly people can get
addicted to the wrong meditation if
they're doing it for the sake of
pleasure yeah they don't be bothered
they don't want to deal with things and
they justify with my meditation practice
yeah that's quite common
so regarding meditation so you sometimes
say that that there is no no jhana
without right view and
things like this maybe maybe i'm quoting
you not quite correctly
not quite correctly
but i mean but we know from the
situation that there were aesthetics for
practice china's without
so no i say there is no right meditation
without the right view i don't say there
is no giant however
having jhana without having right view
today it's almost impossible if you have
janus mean you pretty much have cleared
your mind and developed it because the
reason why the buddha praised the jannah
as the right form of meditation is
because it's along the right uh it's
along the lines of development of the
right view
so
if you that and that's exactly what some
people after being ascetics and followers of
after being ascetics and followers of
different practices
had even his previous teachers neither
perception or perception or higher
states of development
he said they had very little dust in
their eyes on account of it he would
have needed to teach them one sentence
or two so
in other words
the jhana meditation is not what people
think meditation is it's a development
of mind that's basically freeing you
from ignorance even if you don't
necessarily know it
to the extent that the buddha knew it
that's why some people who have
committed like bahia who practiced as a
naked as a wood bark ascetic
for who knows how long
he thought he was generally another hunt
because there was nothing else
disturbing him at all in any shape or
form and then he found out that there is
an actual hunt so he meant to meet a
buddha and all the buddha said is in the
scene let there just be the scene in the
herd in this in the sense to touch the
thought and he became an arahant right
there wow he was so lucky no he did the work
wow he was so lucky no he did the work
probably for decades of his aesthetic
practice which means yes he didn't have the right
which means yes he didn't have the right
view but he was doing the right practice
today that somebody can do the right practice
that somebody can do the right practice
without the right view and develop
genres with all the knowledge of the
suttas that's impossible they would have
to find out that that's what they're
doing but what you have today is people doing
but what you have today is people doing
the opposite stuff that's not found in
the suttas claiming it's the janus from
the suttas and then they'll arrive at
the right view
so the right view
i mean uh
right you you it is not equivalent to a
sense of strain by i mean per se no no
it comes out of sensory strength and
that under understanding the science of
your mind
for what it is yeah but vaginas let's
say sense restraint
sense restraint
and things like that are sufficient
no no no no for jannah sensory strength
is a prerequisite understanding the
entire domain of sensuality the danger
gratification and withdrawal
and then you can dwell in the pleasure
of safety on account of freedom from the
trap and the bait that mata sets up and
then you'll be in ghana
and see all of these things are on the
level of understanding and contemplation
that they would have talked about not on
the level of a meditation technique that
people like to think chanas are
but again they're like i don't know how
many suitors there is no noble aid for
path without the right view let alone
right zamadi without the right view not
possible simply not possible
and what did those ascetic didn't what
did they not understand
i mean who
could practice china's let's say back
then well they obviously understood see they
well they obviously understood see they
they got the genres because they uh
abandoned sensuality completely
that's what would have said an outsider
can um uproot the upper down of centrality
um uproot the upper down of centrality
the purana of the uh
views still about the paramount but they
can't approve the atavada
so that's the only thing that self
review for that you do need buddha's
instruction so but imagine now teaching
freedom from atavada
to putujana who is not free from
sensuality or anything else and i
imagine teaching freedom from atavada to
put ugina who is free from sensuality
and from everything else except that
who's going to what do you think is
going to be easier to teach
and that's exactly the difference one of
them did the work
a lot of it
and that's the problem with the today's
meditation is see even jhana then is
quite a lot of work quite a lot of
clearing the mess from your mind
withdrawal from sensuality seeing the
danger of it
but today's notion of meditation is how
can i avoid all of that work
or or turn my work into something
mindlessly mechanical
that i'll adhere to be told to don't
have to think about too much or doubt or
experience uncertainty
and then i have the experience and
that's the jhana and that's the
sensations and that's the vedanos or
whatever else and that's my liberation
and that's in itself is a completely
wrong direction
what types of meditation do you suggest
are good to practice uh keeping the
precepts guarding of the sense those
uh being mindful moderating your eating
and keep an eye on your intentions
that's samadhi
everything else you do
instead of that it's going to be done
out of the wrong view
if you get the right view if you see the
way out of suffering internally
understand the escape understand the
noble eiffel path then keep the right
view and that will be your somali
protect it that would be your samadhi so
right view means right samadhi no right
view means no right samadhi you can't do
the right meditation without knowing
basically the way out of suffering which
is what the right view is
you do the gradual training the right
way of living
gradual training that's that's all
and there is no mention of such thing as
a meditation technique in a gradual
training ever
in the sutures
gradual training
when you fulfill that when you're ready
for seclusion
withdrawal then you go that next step then you
then you go that next step then you
develop ghana then you dwell in that and
all of the assailants are exhausted and
that's it
everything else that that's today
regarded as meditation and meditation
techniques came probably i don't know
four or five six centuries later
by people they were studying buddhism
not practicing it
and writing booklets instructional
manuals
i mean he he teached different
techniques which ones practice no which ones
which ones practice no which ones
he did that's the point he didn't and
that's what i'm saying
you're welcome to do whatever you want
to do but the most important is don't
misrepresent or don't think that that's
what we lose and many people would think
that oh yeah no that's what the there's
no actually if you read the suttas
you'll find out that he never mentioned
anything like that
and when he did he was mentioned in a
very clear context so now you have a
choice either you carry on with a
contemporary idea of what the buddha was
teaching or find out what buddha was
teaching and then choose which one you want to
and then choose which one you want to
practice but the worst is when people
conflate the two thank you thank you
but
i have a question with regards to this
would you say that for instance
these let's say techniques and
let's say techniques and
okay we don't necessarily have to go
into some of the more contemporary ones
but in general
would you say that they are completely
erroneous or that they were merely an
attempt to formalize
what is in the suttas so that you maybe
do or try to do say sense restraint in a
more systematic manner so that you would
have a certain
form that you could follow
and then you could do this
say right you know see the problem is
can you systematize and formalize your
motivation behind your actions your
states of mind your intentions
can you put that into system i i agree
with that but the thing is that if
somebody knows what he or she is doing
knows what he or she is doing
might be using this formal technique and
it could be helpful because they know
what yeah for instance just for um say having
yeah for instance just for um say having
a more structured way of dealing it and
if you know that you need to be mindful
of or take into account say your
motivation and whatnot this might be
helpful if you don't of course mean that
well i just follow these steps and this
is what is required but you can have
certain steps that allow you to
just you know
have a better way of dealing with
uh background motivations
i'm going to trivialize now but if you
have some sort of a seated meditation
that is focused on something this can be
a useful setting for you to be more
aware of you know which motivations crop
up and working with them now what often
happens that was my experience is that
people just say you know you just sit
and then you follow
breath and if something comes you know
you go back to the breath and one what
not and you completely lose
any sense of that what arises
can be investigated further in in the
right manner but uh so you know you can
either go you can use a technique in a
way that becomes very mechanical or you
can use it as a as a as a tool
um let me draw an analogy for instance
you can you can use say a certain
weightlifting move
just to perfect this particular
weightlifting move and you become a
master snatch or clean uh
or you can use it to improve your
explosiveness because you want to
achieve a certain something right yeah i
understand what you're saying but what
i'm trying to get to the bottom of is
what is the technique
helpful for
what is that carryover snatch carries
over into explosive power
what is your meditation technique
focusing carry over into what is it
helpful for that's that's why i wanna my
response would be for instance that it
could be useful for sense restraint in
the sense of that it allows you a more
structured manner of basically even
coming to terms or seeing the the way
that you are usually not science restrained
you are usually not science restrained
because senses have these tendencies to
go one way or another see now that's the
problem because that perpetrator is the
wrong view where the sense restraint is
said you can't accidentally
break your sense restraint
it's always a matter of choice
it's always a matter of giving in
see but if you think that it's a
question of catching the right moment of
your thoughts that your meditation
technique helps you you are perpetuating
view that the sense restraint or the the
problem of centrality comes from the
world it doesn't it comes from your
choice and that's the whole point
so you cannot systematize your state of
mind if you do it's because you're avoiding
if you do it's because you're avoiding
responsibility for the state of mind
and people have a strong tendency to
systematize because if you stay on the
level of state of mind
you stay on the level of hindrances you
stay on the level of uncertainty doubt
discomfort pressure and that's exactly
what the practice is and that's exactly
where that comes out of a sense
restraint so if you do the precepts rightly you
so if you do the precepts rightly you
are forcing your mind to grow towards
abandoning hindrances and developing
genre whether you want it or not
if you do a technique means you're
managing the symptoms that you don't
want to bear you don't want to endure
the uncertainty you don't want to do the
hindrances you want to systematize it so
you know what to do so you don't endure
the pain so you basically shoot yourself
in the foot
so precepts create to the base for
practice meditation technique took it
away and that's the problem
and that's the problem
and that's why i keep saying if you sit
down to meditate because you're
disturbed you need to calm down fine
then you just need to calm down
but drawing this parallelism oh it's helpful
drawing this parallelism oh it's helpful
to this or that it just perpetuates
along the wrong view of where the
problem is
and it's not in the world it's not in
the sense objects it's not in your
thoughts it's in your choices in regard
to it that the route would increase the
virgin delusion as simple as that
and no systematical way can that always
contain it rightly for everyone
universally because every mind has to see it for
because every mind has to see it for
themselves
okay i i i
especially understand that the point
about uncertainty let me just give
one last attempt maybe in this direction
so the question or my point would be the
following so that
even of course
it is your own response to a certain
something that is crucial um
sometimes it's difficult to basically be
able no not necessarily a response of
any kind well intentional action
intentional action okay okay so
intentional positioning or taking on a
certain attitude towards something yeah
um
sometimes what's problematic is that you
don't really um
things can happen either very quickly or
very messy in a very messy manner and
you kind of lose you you don't really
have a good overview of this so
how technique might be helpful is by
simply you know putting yourself in a
specific position that might be
uncomfortable in many different ways
because people you know there are just
so many different things that crop up
during meditation that that could be
uh uh allow for plenty
of uh
um
that allow a lot of opportunities for
you positioning yourself towards them and in
positioning yourself towards them and in
this regard you can just you know
learn how to recognize your own
um
ways of responding in one way or another
in a slightly
admittedly artificial
environment but at least it gives you
you know an opportunity to
recognize something that might just
elude you otherwise
such as
well for instance you know if you find
yourself um
okay if you find yourself in a very
specific situation say in in the middle
of a city
you know you see an attractive woman
sure and a lot of things happen so
quickly that it is only when it's only
over you know you you realize it if
however if you're in a specific
situation you might get a certain say
thought about a certain person you find
attractive you can notice how you start
responding to it and you
recognize the the the whole event and uh
also can shift your attitude or position
can shift your attitude or position
towards it
a bit better and you know and you learn
to to recognize the difference so you
can see again the problem is not in how
see again the problem is not in how
quickly things move
the problem is in you simply
not knowing where the gateway of your
intention is
and no amount of studying or slowing
down the speed will help you that
again this one perpetuates the wrong
problem thinking that meditation helps you with
thinking that meditation helps you with
what you assume the problem is and
that's not what the problem is
the problem is not how much you're first
of all if you're in that environment
how do you deal with it do you sit
cross-legged in the middle of the road
no you keep the precepts and you endure
the discomfort and you don't let your
eye go where they shouldn't go
don't make choices on account of it and
you already know that that's on the
level of knowledge and cultivation from
beforehand but this idea of slowing down to catch
but this idea of slowing down to catch
my response in the moment again assumes
that the problem is in these involuntary
side sound smell taste touches and it's
not the problem is in
the problem is in
intentional avoidance of discomfort
intentional prolonging of pleasure
intentional distraction and ignoring of
a neutral feeling
and again the more you commit to
watching moments the further away from
recognizing the states of mind you are
of this kind
you get this i just think that you know
there it's it's um
um
sometimes it's difficult or
let's put it differently it takes a
while for one to realize or recognize
just recognize you know the differences
between say a response and reaction
like you said you know nor people
sometimes say well you know things just
happened and you know then
every just a lot of events unfolded but
then if you if you if you start to just
discern or discriminate what is going on
and you acquire this ability to to to
see that then you see that it didn't
just evolve or happen but there were a lot of
evolve or happen but there were a lot of
steps where you basically
took yeah and that's what i'm saying the
yeah and that's what i'm saying the
steps you're taking are not on the level
you're observing
so apples and oranges yeah okay
the steps you are taking are the steps
on the level of choice
that you know in the broader sense
acceptance as would say he welcomes he
delights he entertains the notions of sensuality
he entertains the notions of sensuality
so say you saw some something that
attracted your attention on the street
you looked once now you feel bad you
realize and there is a choice there do i
look again do i give in to the weakness
or do i undo the pain
and there's no meditation technique
there's no place for meditation that is
a
meditation i understand so due to this
comfort of not letting it he doesn't let
the eyes look at the unsuitable things
he doesn't let ear go to the domain of
unsuitable sounds they will provoke lust
infatuation and in those states of mind
and that's not on the level of
mechanical watching of the moments
analyzing the slowing down the speed
that's on the level of choice
and that's not something you can have in
front of you as a object of your senses
that you can observe or focus on okay
but i mean
so in my experience in meditation let's
say some meditation techniques
it seems so when sebastian explains what
he does it seems to me that i am doing
something similar and it seems like it
helps you to do
[Music] let's say
let's say
right choices i'd say or not to do bad
choices but simply because you are more
aware of the things that's going on so
to say
like i and it can't be helpful in this
way i mean like um
there i mean maybe you you would notice
it also without this technique but but
it still helps you to to come back
faster so let's say come back to what
well to the choice that you just just
done or said let's say you you did it
you you looked in the direction where
you shouldn't have looked uh-huh and and
well i mean normally you would continue
in this direction and only afterwards to
see okay i shouldn't have done this but
in in when i say when the mind is count
through meditation you can recognize
this well just at the moment when you
when you just looked and uh just
made one glance in the
in
no but see now you're talking about the
environment when you're not calm in the
environment when you're come yeah so
which one is it do you sit in the middle
of the road to calm your mind no but or
you're talking about a different
instance well i mean i i'd say that that
meditation has an
impact also on european it means a mixer
road i'd say uh so it's a it's like
it's like this general i mean you also
speak saying about speaking about
sensory strain that sort of holds you
even amidst it's a situation which is
not really um
well supporting it so i'd say the same
supporting it so i'd say the same
about the calmness of mind yeah i'm not
denying the calmness of mind i'm denying
that the focus in practice results in
contributing to you know your intentions
because what are you focusing on can you
focus on the intention of your mind
what is the object of your focusing
in your meditation that's my question i
suppose well yeah i mean it's how should
i say for me it's i mean i shouldn't
call it focusing really but it's it's
more like
you try to to to
to stay somehow with your breath and and
it's like putting some
and observe your intentions
on its on on its background
so it's it's like i'd say yeah sorry
sorry sorry
absorb the intentions observe sorry
observe yeah observe your intentions
more like just to watch what you're
thinking about and try not to say not to
get caught in them
in a manner that you sort of
i mean how do you how do you get caught
in thoughts well when you start um
dealing too much with the content let's
say if you i mean if you're
um
let's say you have some some golden
problem whatever
and you you start solving it instead of
let's say trying to understand why am i
thinking about it what is
i mean more general perspective what are
my intentions basically
in all this stuff so
um i'd say like so how does that
meditation technique
help you understand the intentions and
not be caught up yeah so i'd say it's
i'm it seems to me that it's over if i
may use a similarly it seems to me it's
like uh um
having like a let's say a white table
and and putting um
something that you want you want to sort
out on this white table and so that you
can see clearly where the where the
things are and another situation is like
when you when you mine is confused it's
like having like sure yeah
great and that's exactly what not but
problem is not
so having things cluttered
or sorted out
you already have intention behind you
already have an intention to sort things
out because they bother you
you're already bothered by things that
are not sorted out on the level your
intentions you can't sort your
intentions like you would sort things on
the table
so when you want to sort out your
thoughts you do that because you want to avoid
you do that because you want to avoid
suffering you don't want to endure it
you don't want to be unmoved by it you
want to get rid of it
or when you just revolve spinning out of
control you do that because you don't
want to avoid suffering
either way you're managing the pain
either way meditation techniques is
taking in the directions away
from where your intentions are because
both are rooted in intention of avoiding
pain and that's the problem
and that's the problem
and no amount of looking and sorting
things out and catching the details
will change the intention that all of
that is rooted in
because as i said already and also it
perpetuates the wrong view that the mind
gets disturbed by things and speed of
things and that's not true that is a
completely wrong view the what the
buddha described the root of every
disturbance in the mind is greed
aversion and delusion
things that you do by choice and
intention so too many women passing you does not
so too many women passing you does not
disturb your mind too many sounds
disturbing your ear does not disturb
your mind
choosing greed choosing a version
choosing the illusion disturbs your mind
so now you have a meditation technique
that helps you calm the disturbed mind
and at the same time perpetuates the
view that the disturbance came of the
world and things moving too fast
so your meditation techniques keeps you
wrong if you're evolving because it
doesn't recognize the weight disturbance
didn't come from things being too quick
or too slow or too many or one or too
few it came because i still choose
aversion delusion and greed when they
present themselves i haven't endured
things on the right level i haven't
upgraded a seal on the right level i
don't see the danger in the slightest
fault on the right level i'm not
moderate enough i don't live in secret
whatever parts of the gradual training
that the buddha listed as a prerequisite
you must be lacking somewhere because if
you don't the mind would not be
disturbed because there are no more
choices and intentions rooted in great
diversion delusion thus if the mind is
not disturbed what use is to calm it by
sorting the tools on the table if you
need to sort them out great but has
nothing to do with the development of
where the problem is the gateway
but and say like being in seclusion i
mean it's also
it's also
i mean
it's it's a question to what extent you
can be in seclusion let's say even in
the monastic environment yeah so i mean
uh it maybe i could say that it's not
it's because i'm lacking in seclusion as
much as probably is
needed no i don't think seclusion i just
listed those examples i don't think
that's a problem for most people that
comes later even the seclusion in the
gradual training comes far later
first person the person develops the
right view becomes a solar panel and
then he's ready for seclusion seclusion
for most people seclusion is just oh
just again
some sort of controlled environment that
will not disturb me as much
because i don't know how to deal with
the disturbances that come because i
don't see where the gateway is that's
fine but you need to recognize again the
only way to start practicing rightly is
to recognize where that gateway is
and it's not in speed of things it's not
in the environment environment around
you it's not in the sense object it's
not in anything observable it's not in
your body
gateway is welcoming delighting
entertaining breed aversion delusion
that's why literally when someone said
give me one one just short instructions
there as they would and he would say
whatever you know that is unwholesome
rooted greater version delusion don't do
it
thank you
three months later our hands
because that is okay so i use that as a
standard greed diversion delusion on the level of
greed diversion delusion on the level of
thought speech your mind i would endure
did not act out of it i will not do
anything on account of it
and that's how it will fade but it needs
to be brought up to that absolute core
level and if it's not on that level it's
and if it's not on that level it's
because the gradual training has not
been taken up sufficiently
restrained by the rules seeing danger in
the slightest fault
not only all this is allowable there's
no such thing if it's rooted in three
diverse delusion it's not allowable even
if it's not against the presets
and that's the principle that most
people don't take on as a practice
they take concealer but they don't take
the practice on account of it
so that's what i mean you you can be
calm in your mind with various
techniques but you've got to be aware at
the same time you're perpetuating the
wrong view of where the problem really
is
and it's not there
because the disturbances do not come on
account of you not having watched your
thoughts enough
or you know the world overwhelming you
or something no it comes on a kind of
intentional choice of greed aversion
delusion every single time
so you stop doing those the mind will
have to come down whether you want it or
not so you have to watch your thoughts all
so you have to watch your thoughts all
the time no no you have to watch your
choices choices
yeah
but would you would you say that for
instance um
okay let's leave aside the
the term technique
okay it's two to two uh
it's two to two uh
ladder
uh with connotations so um
maybe ways or creating
conditions circumstances where you um
that's for me the reason why i'm asking
all this because this for me was
important in the sense of
even learning to recognize
greed for instance or delusion you know
it's it's one thing to say it but then
what do you think how it manifests well
so hold on what makes you think you
recognized it
well i mean
i mean
you you you know it when it manifests
itself but you you
so for instance you know what this term
which phenomena designates however it's
sometimes difficult to see how it
manifests in
specific contexts
so what it means for you so how how it
affects you in very concrete context so
give an example
an example of
seeing the illusion and seeing the
specific context of delusion what do you
mean by it okay
maybe you know maybe i can take greed or
something okay
[Music] it would be just um
for instance uh uh
during the the the um
the seated meditation or what have you
and uh um having something appear in
your mind and then just seeing how um
how entangled and you become and how
how the emotive responses are towards
that where you want to simply cling to that
where you want to simply cling to that
or you you you don't want to
get away from that particular thing and
then the thing itself you realize it's
not really that important but the
overall uh response that was evoked is
and why is that a problem yeah because
you you you feel that
ah because it's painful
it's unpleasant so you want to get rid
of this comfort
uh
i see where you're going
he comes back to that acting out of
feeling yeah
and that's that's my point yeah yeah but
i mean so so you recognize
that the pain is the problem so you
analyzing your responses i will rooted
you just because you don't want this
pain to be here so
you are acting out of aversion towards
pain yeah but see
that way you can recognize a version
again so well you you haven't
so well you you haven't
see you're recognizing what you placed
in front to be but see you think you're
now understanding greed and stuff while in
understanding greed and stuff while in
reality you're currently in the state of
aversion that you're fully gripped and
you're not seeing
because you're looking at something you
think is creed
okay so it's it's obviously and again mind
so it's it's obviously and again mind
you none of these i'm not i'm not saying
you shouldn't sit down quietly in a
non-disturbed environment and think
about things
because whenever you started to describe
to me your meditation you don't you
describe basically you sit down and you
start thinking about things
well that was just you know i there are ways
that was just you know i there are ways
of maybe just and that's absolutely fine
yeah you don't want to be in the middle
of the city and i must be able to
meditate here no you probably won't be
able to
or even contemplate things so you want
to calm down
but then yeah you need to recognize
where the problem is
and the problem is always in
present action routinely presently and
during feeling okay
and even if that's unclear
or sometimes it's more clear sometimes
not that clear
that comes and goes what doesn't come
and go is presets virtue tangent the
slightest fault and
you still do see your intentions and
states of mind on that level yeah maybe
you don't see it on the subtlest level
of the thought but it's only because
obviously you're still in some level
welcoming it elsewhere not because you
haven't you know caught a right moment
to spot it because it's not only a train
has passed
oh i missed it now no state of mind and
yours you are the state of mind
so if you're unclear about it it's not
because it evaded you it's because you
haven't sufficiently stopped acting out
of great vision delusion you stopped you
haven't sufficiently stopped
entertaining it and welcoming it hence
the disturbances are still present in
the mind can you give
an example of how to
preserve the choices
well if you get up in the morning and
basically see what you want to do
and then see why you want to do those
things in the most generic way
like oh i want to go and see such and
such why
is that rooted why am i bored at home am
i lonely do i need company do i just
want a distraction or you know i'm going
to learn or something and already all
these choices are there you just need to
start asking those questions to yourself
so so that's the practice that's the the
um that's the contemplation and then you
see where intentions well then spend
every day of your life
not acting out of anything that's rooted
in sensual desire
in aversion and distraction
and the purification of the mind
will have to happen whether you want it
or not
and that is much harder
to do and keep an eye on trump see oh
now okay so now i have to change my
lifestyle as well
i can go left and right and pay no
attention to things around me
if i have to you know
restrain my own intentions it's not
going to be possible
so that's the whole lifestyle choices
then start to change and so on
and that's much more fundamental and
much more harder than if either you know
your duties sit for half an hour
calm down feel the sensations watch your
nostrils and then go about your life
no people never said that anything
remotely like that he was always yeah
you want to improve your life stop
acting out of great division delusion to
the extent you stop acting out of those
states of mind to that extent your mind
will be more peaceful more pliable it
will listen to you it will be more
trained you do it more great it will be even
you do it more great it will be even
more so
and and that's the that's the practice
of pretty much
they would take you from somebody who
doesn't have the right view to somebody
who has the right view and then from
somebody who had the right view could
take you to abandon centrality and
everything else
because these as i said these
disturbances that nobody wants even
people that don't practice
want to practice nobody wants to disturb
mind they don't come on a car to the
world they don't come on account of
anything through your senses they come
on account of your choices
that's the only place they can come
through and that's what they would have
meant by that even if the highway
robbers are chopping your limbs if you
hate them you haven't fulfilled my
teaching because that's not the problem
your limbs being chopped was not a
problem it was you acting out of a virgin
it was you acting out of a virgin
so if you're able to hate them means oh
you have not uprooted it
and what if you
enjoy nature for example that's not a
problem that's also central pleasure to some
that's also central pleasure to some
extent well it depends it's like uh
it's not necessarily always going to be
rooted in the same motivation
so it's not outside never go into nature
no just after each time you want to go
into nature you have to know why you're
doing it
are you doing it just you know yeah you
want some nature peaceful freedom from
people or are you doing it because you
know you're a bit bored
lonely in your apartment she's like
awesome now you're doing it because you
want to avoid discomfort and another
occasion you might do it because you
need exercise or something
so it's not it's not set in stone every
single time
but how does someone know what is desire
when [Music]
[Music]
he speaks about going into woods or
meditating or
being avoid of
suffering this can be desires also
this can be desires also
but it's
beneficial what what can be desired also not
what what can be desired also not
desired for not being
for not suffering desire for going goods
and uh having right right right yeah
yeah yeah yeah sure that's that's what
meant desire is to be abandoned by the means
desire is to be abandoned by the means
of desire
so
because of that desire
yeah you will now start keeping the
precepts not acting out of desire and
you will lose all the desires
will you lose them
well again now you're guessing because
you're not at the end stage of not
having any desire so unless you commit
to the path and free yourself from
desire you won't know for yourself
whether you're going to lose them or not
so whichever answer i give you is going
to be a speculative one what's the point
i have a question
about breath did buddha
did buddha
just talk about
being present and watch your
breath in manner of gas exchange or did he
in manner of gas exchange or did he
speak about
some energies about prana about uh qi uh uh
well first
he he spoke about
anapanasati the mindfulness
of or not non-forgetfulness of breathing
to people that already had the right
view so they already knew what you know
so they already knew what you know
freedom from desire is freedom from
suffering and so on
and then the way he spoke about it it's
no it nothing to do with like prana or
energies it was more of a just mindfulness of
it was more of a just mindfulness of
your choice to breathe
i should breathe in like this i should
breathe out like that i should breathe
in with a state of mind like this
actually breathing with the state of
mind of that and that's it
so it was quite different from the uh
other kind of breeding practices
of india
at the time i don't know if it's the
same time or around the same time but uh
yeah had not had absolutely no
connotations of any
energies or things like that to be
developed it was just pure
non-forgetfulness just so you're mindful
just so you're mindful
that's what's called mindfulness of
breathing
i have a question in in this
similar lines
so
it seems to me that well
it was this the same
that i was uh that i wanted to refer to
actually the desire
has to be abandoned by means of desire
maybe i mean abortion and also by the
minister aversion
but i mean like
isn't it
if somebody meditates in order to get
rid of um certain wholesome states
can't it be uh regarded as well as a
wholesome aversion or a wholesome desire
like well yes if your meditation is right
well yes if your meditation is right
but as i said if your meditation
perpetuates the view of where the
problem is when it isn't there
then it's not then it's just on account
of desire on account wanting to be free
from desire unintentionally doing things
that are increasing your desire
so that's why it matters what you do not
everything will free you from desire but
yes everybody needs to want to have a
desire to be free from these desires
because they're so unpleasant
but how you go about it that's now the
difference
so basically it's uh
not that uh not that this um let's say
desire to to get rid of understand but i
think is a problem but the problem is
the wrong approach
yeah exactly yeah like as i said you
know when when
he doesn't welcome he doesn't entertain
you know you can go differently about
those things like the thoughts of
sensuality you could just i will not
think that yeah that's one way of
getting rid of or you could oh i shall
not open the door for this and they will
leave that's another way to get rid of
but they are mutually exclusive you
either have to open the door and get
into a fight
and try to deny it or chase it and
exhaust yourself and abandon the gateway
or you simply recognize wait as long as
i don't open the door they can't come in
so yeah they might shout and scream in
front of the door which is what i used
to find unpleasant which is why i opened
the door and tried to calm my mind
but that's not where the calmness was
the calmness was is recognizing the
gateway protecting it as the weather
said you find a city with only one
entrance one in and out and you stand there
one in and out and you stand there
and you see who comes in who knows in
this case in my similar you don't open
the door and they leave so either way
you haven't welcomed it
[Music] so so that's that's that's what i'm
so so that's that's that's what i'm
saying like
there is there is a difference in the
way a person would go about it and
that's pretty much determining the
intentions behind why you're doing it
and then you will know whether it's an
immediate version of i don't want this
pain or if it's like a broader picture
oh yeah i am practicing towards freedom
from desire in that ultimate sense
wisdom is not on the level of um
intellectual answers yeah it's on the
level of being in control of your mind
not losing perspective
that's like the wise perspective person
who is wise is the person who has
perspective on things
who is not caught up in details of them
so and you developed that by by
everything we've been describing
uh do you have a name for the state
where someone
can manipulate emotions and feelings
um in a manner of
um just like driving a boat
uh a boat has it bad
uh
this path is like emotion
okay now we are in a motion of joy or or
now we are in a motion of joy or or
anger or something this is a boat and
now someone can just turn the wheel
and we go into another emotion or no emotion
we go into another emotion or no emotion
he can stop it he can and this uh
process is like seconds
like controlling emotions yes
uh no no certainly in in the buddhist
teaching that's
that's not how emotions are described
okay if you were to have a control over
emotions you wouldn't have been in a
boat that goes in the direction of pain
to begin with
that was the buddhist point
so you might act out of emotions
and create new ones
and distract yourself with centrality
but fundamentally you are subjected to
them first
so if you were truly in control of them
you would never experience pain because
nobody wants pain
and if you're a master means the pain
would not be able to manifest itself
but the fact that it does manifest
itself even if you quickly evade it
means well yeah but you are still
subjected to emotions first which is why
they still come when they want to come
which means
time will come when you will not be able
to steer the boat to pleasure and you
want to recognize that before that time
comes like what we said and that's the
whole training